A Finding Aid to the Dorothy Varian Papers, circa 1902-1984, in the Archives of American Art AAA.varidoro
Archives of American Art
Dorothy Varian papers
circa 1902-1984
AAA.varidoro
Archives of American Art
2.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter Dorothy Varian date from circa 1902 to 1984 and measure 2.3 linear feet. This collection documents Varian's life primarily through scattered biographical material; correspondence with family, friends, artists and art galleries; personal business records; a few writings; exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material; photographs of Varian, her friends, and artwork; and original sketches by Varian and fellow artist Peggy Bacon.
Varian, Dorothy, 1895-1987
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Dorothy Varian (1895-1985) was a painter in New York City, and Woodstock, NY. Varian was born in New York City on April 26, 1895; daughter of Eugene W. and Helen Estelle Varian. She dropped out of high school at 15 and entered Cooper Union where she graduated with honors. After Cooper Union she attended the Art Students League. While a student she inadvertently won first and second prize in a local art contest sponsored by movie producer, William Fox. She used the prize money to rent her first studio in Woodstock.
In 1920, her cousins Jessie and C. Vanderbilt Barton provided her the means to study in Paris. Varian’s first one-man show was held in 1922 at the Durand-Ruel Galleries in Paris. A close friend of Varian’s during this time was Jean Renior, son of Pierre-Auguste Renoir. Within the first year after she returned permanently to the United States, Varian had exhibitions at the Whitney Club, Whitney Galleries, and the Downtown Galleries. Edith Halpert, director of the Downtown Galleries became Varian’s art dealer. Varian used the money from her work to buy a home in Woodstock which became her primary painting studio. The majority of her circle was formed during her time at the Art Students League and during her years in Paris. Varian also met many artists who were living and working alongside her in Woodstock. Throughout her life, she stayed in contact with many of these friends including Peggy Bacon, Alex Brook, Georgina Klitgaard, Frederick Dana Marsh, Lenore G. Marshall, and Waldo Pierce.
Varian worked primarily with watercolor and oil painting. Varian’s work has been exhibited at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Corcoran Galleries, Carnegie International, Whitney Museum of American Art, Association of American Artists Gallery, Brooklyn Museum, and several universities across the country. Over the course of her career, Varian held fifteen solo exhibitions and received many awards including the Kuniyoshi Award in 1975. Varian died in 1985 at the age of 90.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1920-1980 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1917-1981 (0.8 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, 1940s-1960s (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1931-1984 (9 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1916-1981 (0.5 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1902-1961 (13 folders; Boxes 2-3)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1912-1924 (11 folders; Boxes 2-3)
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 797 and 833 at the Archives of American Art offices, and thorugh interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the current arrangement of this collection does not match the microfilm arrangement.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in installments by Dorothy Varian in 1972, 1978, and 1981. An additonal installment was donated in 1986 by the Dorothy Varian estate, via Robert Plate.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in this repository is an interview of Dorothy Varian conducted 1980 Dec. 6-7, by Avis Berman, for the Archives of American Art.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Dorothy Varian date from circa 1902 to 1984 and measure 2.3 linear feet. This collection documents Varian's life primarily through scattered biographical material; correspondence with family, friends, artists and art galleries; personal business records; a few writings; exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material; photographs of Varian, her friends, including Peggy Bacon, Alex Brook, Bernard Karfiol, and Yasuo Kuniyoshi, and artwork; and original sketches by Varian and fellow artist Peggy Bacon.
Varian’s earliest correspondence is with her mother and her cousin Jessie, detailing her life as an artist in Paris. Also found is extensive correspondence with with Peggy Bacon, Hermine Kleinert, Lenore G. Marshall, Waldo Pierce, Katherine Schmidt, Antoinette Schulte, and the Renoir family.
Bacon, Peggy, 1895-1987; Brook, Alexander, 1898-1980; Karfiol, Bernard, 1886-1952; Klienert, Herminie; Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, 1889-1953; Marshall, Lenore, 1897-1971; Peirce, Waldo, 1884-1970; Schmidt, Katherine, 1898-1978; Schulte, Antoinette E., 1897-1981; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Sketches; Women painters -- New York (State) -- New York
- Biographical Material, 1920-1980; Series 1; 5 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes U.S. passports and French identification papers. Also found are an annotated resume and curriculum vitae as well as the Archives of American Art oral history transcript for an interview conducted by Avis Berman, which was also annotated by Varian. One 5-inch sound tape reel includes an interview of Dorothy Varian conducted by Karl Fortess.
  - Identification Records, 1959-1965; 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Excerpts, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronology and Resumes, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Organization Memberships, 1955 October 22-November 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oral History Interview by Karl Fortess, 1969 June; 1973; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annotated Oral History Transcript, 1980 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1917-1981; Series 2; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name. Additional correspondence with galleries can be found within Personal Business Records.
  The majority of this series consists of personal correspondence between Varian and friends and family members. Varian’s earliest correspondence is with her parents, Eugene and Helen, and with her cousins, Jessie and Vanderbilt during her years in Paris. Extensive correspondence is with Peggy Bacon, Hermine Kleinert, Lenore G. Marshall, Waldo Pierce, Katherine Schmidt, Antoinette Schulte, and the Renoir family. Varian also received a number of illustrated letters from Frederick Dana Marsh and others. Also of note are holiday and greeting cards Varian sent to her friends and colleagues.
  - A, Miscellaneous, circa 1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bacon, Peggy, 1920-1930; 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Barton, Jessie and C. Vanderbilt, 1920-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Brook, Alexander, 1920-1921; 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - B, Miscellaneous, 1921-1937; 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1934-1939; 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Durand-Ruel, Paul and Madge, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - D, Miscellaneous, 1959-1961; 1921 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - E, Miscellaneous, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - F, Miscellaneous, circa 1934; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1922-1933; 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1930-1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Includes letters from Edith Halpert and Isabella Howland.
  - J, Miscellaneous, 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes letters from Edward Alden Jewell and James Dudley.
  - Kleinert, Hermine E., 1921; 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1925-1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Includes letters from Georgina Kiltgaard, Manuel Komroff, and Yasuo Kuniyoshi.
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1917; 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Includes letters from Reeves Lewenthal.
  - Marsh, Frederick Dana, 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Marshall, Lenore G., 1941-1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1944; 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - N, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - O, Miscellaneous, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Peirce, Waldo and Alzira, 1928-1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1922-1930; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Renoir, Jean and Andree, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - R, Miscellaneous, 1921; 1948-1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Schmidt, Katherine (Mrs. Irvine Shubert), circa 1920s; 1955-1977 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Schulte, Antoinette, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - S, Miscellaneous, 1924-1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Includes letters from Homor Saint-Gaudens, Eugene Speicher, and Alfred Stiegliz.
  - T, Miscellaneous, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Unidentified, circa 1920s; 1960 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Varian, Eugene W., 1920s (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Z, Miscellaneous, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Includes letters from Armando Zegri.
  - Greeting Cards, undated; 1920s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 43-47)
  - Unidentified Letter Envelopes, 1920-1980 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Writings, 1940s-1960s; Series 3; 3 Folders Box 1
  This series contains a sample of Varian’s poetry and essays. There are also miscellaneous notes and drafts of poems. Some of the writings in the series are "Letter to the Editor" pieces while others are essays on art and the artist.
  - Poems, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Essays, 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Personal Business Records, 1931-1984; Series 4; 9 Folders Box 1
  Personal business records primarily include art gallery commission and exhibition records. These records come from galleries across the country, particularly the Carnegie Institute, Downtown Gallery, and Whitney Museum of American Art. Other records included in this series are transaction receipts of art sales, inventories and price lists.
  - Carnegie Institute, 1931-1945 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Downtown Gallery, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - A-M, Miscellaneous, 1936-1982 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Includes records from The Art Institute of Chicago, The Art Students League, and the American Artists Group.
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1940-1980 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Wichita State University, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Yasuo Kuniyoshi Fund Inc., 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - N-Z, Miscellaneous, 1934-1984 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Lists of Artwork and Price Lists, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Records of Art Sales, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Printed Material, 1916-1981; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 2
  Printed material primarily includes exhibition catalogs and announcements and newspaper clippings. Exhibition materials are for works by Varian as well of exhibitions by other artists. Of note is a 1926 Brancusi exhibition catalog inscribed to Varian. Some newspaper clippings document the acitivities of friends and fellow artists Peggy Bacon and Bernard Karfiol. Also included is a book of poetry, Tease the Tiger’s Nose which Varian illustrated.
  - Gallery and Exhibition Publications, 1920-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibitions Announcements, 1920-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1920s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 5-10)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - News Clippings, 1916-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - News Clippings regarding Bernard Karfiol, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Published Books, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Art Students League 1919 issue of "Bad News" for which Varian was the Assistant Editor.
- Photographs, circa 1902-1961; Series 6; 13 Folders Boxes 2-3
  This series includes professional portraits of Varian and her artwork. There are additionally photos of exhibit installations taken at Long Island University in 1961. The series also contains more candid, personal photos of Varian with friends and family. Of note are photographs of friends Peggy Bacon, Alex Brook, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, and Bernard Karfiol. Though the majority of these personal photos are from Varian’s mid-to-late adult life, there are a few photos of Varian as a child.
  - Portraits of Dorothy Varian, 1916-1937 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1902-1950s (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1922-1949 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Installations, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Peggy Bacon and Alex Brook with Children, circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Bernard Karfiol, undated (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
  - Oversized Personal Photograph, circa 1934 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Photograph of Artwork, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Artwork, circa 1912-1920s; Series 7; 11 Folders Boxes 2-3
  This series primarily consists of pencil sketches done by Varian during her time at the Art Students League and in Paris. The sketches feature a mixture of human and landscape subjects. In addition to the sketches created by Varian, the series also includes sketches by Peggy Bacon and Edmund Duffy. Also found are a small selection of handmade greeting cards.
  - Greeting Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Sketches, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Sketches, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sketches, 1910s-1920s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Sketches, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Sketches, circa 1921-1924 (Box 2, Folder 39-41)
  - Sketches by Edmund Duffy, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Sketches by Peggy Bacon, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Oversized Sketch, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)